You have been a busy guy in your
profession. A couple of quotes that I
want to attribute to you and you can own
them or not. I want to be sure I'm
right. One is you said I exposed the CIA
and went to prison for it. That
something you said. Uh it is. You said
there are some things we should not do
even in the name of national security.
Is that something you said? Indeed it
is. All right. This is something that
you took very
seriously in your life. Why did you go
into the CIA? Were you recruited? I was
recruited in graduate school, but to
tell you the truth, I was only
considering uh jobs in public service.
I'm the grandson of four uh uh
grandparents who immigrated to this
country from Greece. And in our
household while I was growing up, uh it
was instilled in all of us really that
that we owed this country such a great
debt of thanks for giving us a new life
in this wonderful country that we needed
to pay that debt back. And so my parents
were elementary school teachers in the
public school system and they instilled
in us the notion that we should go into
public service as well. So, you went
into public service, but you didn't sit
around in the sandbox as a kid
envisioning yourself being a CIA agent.
Actually, I did uh when I was nine, I
told my parents that I wanted to be a
spy when I grew up. And they bought me
uh walkie-talkies for for Christmas that
year. I remember. Yeah. And then when I
was 16, I said specifically, I I
remember telling my father that not only
did I want to be a spy, but I wanted to
be a spy in the Middle East. And so I um
I went to George Washington University
and got a an undergraduate degree in
Middle Eastern studies. Uh, I stayed at
GW for a master's degree in legislative
affairs, but with a concentration in
foreign policy analysis, thinking if I
can't get into the CIA, I'll go to
Capitol Hill or I'll go to the foreign
service. And then, as it turned out, my
graduate school advisor
uh, who gave me an A on a paper, it was
a psychology exam, asked me to, he wrote
in the in the margin of the paper,
please see me after class. So I went to
see him and he said, 'Look, I'm not
really a professor here. I'm a CIA
officer undercover as a professor here
and I'm looking for people who might fit
into the CIA's culture. Would you like
to be a CIA officer? And I jumped at the
chance and the next thing I knew, I had
my right hand in the air and I was
swearing an oath to uphold the
Constitution.
Wow. So he was he was kind of taking a
chance because he was undercover. So, he
was actually Let's talk about that for a
minute because I have an
issue with some of what's going on in
the elite universities of the United
States right now. And I'm wondering if
we're sending our kids to get educated
or
indoctrinated. What do you say about
that?
Right. that is going to be a fight that
we are going to have to fight from here
on out. I will say that the way that I
was uh uh recruited into the CIA is no
longer legal. With passage in 1993 of
the Equal Employment Opportunity Act,
you can't do this old boy network. But
what they do now is they just do it out
in public. The CIA created this this uh
program called the Scholar and Residence
Program. So if you've done your 25 or 30
years, you're planning to retire,
they'll send you back to your alma mater
for 2 or 3 years, you can teach some
meaningless class like a friend of mine
went back to Indiana University and
taught uh espionage in Soviet literature
and
uh and students will just go up to him
after class and say, "Hey, I'd love to
get into the CIA." And he makes a
recommendation. So rather than do it to
do it behind closed doors like they did
it with me, they just do it out in the
open now.
Okay. So we actually do have
professors in universities now that
aren't necessarily who they seem to be.
Correct.
They are actually operatives, CIA
operatives or maybe from other agencies
that are there to indoctrinate, to
recruit. What What are they there for?
Why are they in those roles? Oh, it's a
combination of the two. They're always
looking for people with hard foreign
languages or people who have an aptitude
for difficult foreign languages. They're
looking for people who are patriotic on
their face, patriotic, and if they think
that you can fit into that culture, and
it's it's deeper than just, you know,
fitting into the culture. I I've said uh
in many podcasts that a CIA psychiatrist
once told me that the CIA actively seeks
to hire people who have sociopathic
tendencies, not sociopaths. Because, of
course, sociopaths have no conscience.
They blow right through a polygraph
exam, but they're impossible to control.
People who have sociopathic tendencies
do have a conscience. They do react to
the polygraph, but at the same time,
they're happy to operate in these moral,
legal, and ethical gray areas. I I
remember when I was when I was going
through the interview process, um there
were four or five of us there and uh and
the instructor said, "Let's say you're a
CIA officer and you get a cable from
headquarters telling you to uh recruit
the Indonesian economic secretary
because you need some Indonesian
economic information." And you cultivate
this relationship for a year. you become
friends, your wives become friends, you
vacation together, but you you come to
realize that he's not recruitable. What
do you do? And a guy put his hand up in
the air and said, "Well, you double
down. You do it another 6 months." A
woman raised her hand and said, "Uh,
maybe you can work it through the
wives." And I'm looking around looking
at these people. I put my hand up and I
said, "You break into the embassy and
you steal it." And the instructor said,
"That's exactly what you do." Well, I
came to learn that's a sociopathic
tendency. Do you have sociopathic
tendencies? Probably. Uh, I was
perfectly happy to break into people's
homes or offices overseas and plant bugs
or plant cameras. I was perfectly happy
to convince people that I was their best
friend to the point where they were wi
willing to commit espionage for me or in
some cases treason because I believed we
were the good guys and I was doing this
uh for the safety and security of of
Americans and American installations.
And so I never gave it a second thought
beyond the fact that we were the good
guys. So you say the CIA hires people
with sociopathic tendencies and you say
sociopaths have concise answers and pass
polygraph tests. Sociopaths are
impossible to control. They slip through
the cracks because they have no
conscience. And they only hire
sociopathic narcissists. The CI
operatives look for narcissistic
individuals because they're so arrogant.
They conclude, "Of course, the CIA would
want to recruit me because I'm so
important that they cannot do their jobs
without me." Oh my goodness. You see
that every single day of your career.
You are surrounded by the smartest, the
most accomplished,
uh the the best educated, at least all
in their own minds people. Uh it it
becomes comical after a while. Yeah. You
actually don't see that so much in
analysis. It's in operations where
everybody wants to be James Bond. And in
some cases, they actually achieve that.
You know, there there is always a
handful of senior officers that all the
rest of us wanted to be like, people who
had many recruitments, people who had uh
multiple chief of station assignments.
That's that's what everybody was
aspiring to. And and you get it by what
they used to call, not jokingly,
shameless self-promotion. Yeah. Now,
were you that way? Is that why they
picked you? Was it languages? Why did
they pick you? Were you a sociopathic
narcissist? In retrospect, I I probably
had those sociopathic tendencies, but
they picked me. I I actually spent the
first half of my career in analysis.
They picked me
because because I had uh Arabic language
um and because I I was very serious
about academia. I was very serious about
analysis and study and I I was
fascinated by Arab culture and Arab
history. I read Arab poetry. I studied
Islam uh under one of the most important
uh Islamic scholars in the western
world. I I was just fascinated with that
culture and I wanted to live there and
really get to understand people and so I
went to the directorate of intelligence,
the analytic uh branch and succeeded not
necessarily because I was so great but
because I was really lucky. Just as I
got to a point where I felt like I knew
what I was doing, Iraq invaded Kuwait on
August the 2nd, 1990. I was the only
Iraq leadership analyst. And I remember
walking in that morning and saying uh to
my boss, "Big day ahead of us today."
And he said, "Don't take your jacket
off. We're going to the Oval Office." I
was 25 years old. And I walk in and it's
the president, the vice president, the
national security adviser, the CIA
director, my boss, and me. And we all
sit down. The president looks around and
he says, "Well, now what do we do?" And
then everybody turned and looked at me.
And I remember thinking to myself, my
friends from high school would never
believe it in a million years if I told
them what I was doing right now. So I I
got lucky there.